do
[Music]
hello greetings everybody welcome to the
95th live episode of ask a budget
uh let's see who all is there tonight
with us i can see someone gosh kapil
abhinav
and lots of other people greetings to
all of you it's great to have you all
tonight
and uh
so today i'm gonna take questions from
the comments
so let's get right into it and let's
begin today's tonight's episode
so let's go with the first question it's
uh a couple of questions rolled into one
so pro legend says you said that if a
country has its military stationed in
another country or as a military base in
another country that country is
essentially under occupation so if we
think that way india has a military base
in tajikistan mauritius and some other
countries so are these countries under
indian occupation and bobby says by your
logic oman is occupied by india there
needs to be a distinction between why a
base is placed and for what reason it's
placed japan is allied with the u.s
since the end of world war ii
just because japan has an american base
does not mean it's occupied it is
incorrect misleading terminology used to
describe the situation
japan has its own autonomy and has the
sovereignty of its own land the policies
of the government are controlled
exclusively by japan they have
tri-branch parliamentary system as with
most democracies executive and so on
it also has an emperor as the head of
state as for serving its best interests
japan has an alliance with the us they
also have foregone
what's that
foregone specific elements of its
military in exchange for american
support all right all right very nice
so
let's examine logically so first of all
i've never said that if you have a
military base in another country it
means you're occupy you're occupying the
country i said
permanent
military bases signify occupation
permanent military bases not a
transactional relationship so let's
let's examine the relationship between
india and oman and indian tajikistan for
instance
so let's ask these questions firstly
has india defeated tajikistan and
mauritius and oman in a war
no
india has not
has india
forced tajikistan or mauritius or oman
to allow india to keep a military base
there on their soil
no india has not has india nuked
no india has not has india forced
tajikistan or mauritius or oman
to adopt a constitution that has been
written by indians
no india has not
has india does india have a permanent
military
base or bases in these countries for
decades on end
no india does not
what india does have is a very friendly
cordial warm
relationship based on mutual respect and
mutual interests with these nations
so india
has
negotiated with these countries
and they have accepted
india's offer
to emplace a military base on their
territory
and i expect india must be paying them
handsomely for that privilege of using
their territory for india's purposes and
i'm sure there are other aspects to the
relationship as well india and mauritius
have very close relations because of
this ethnicity and history so they trust
india
they know india is not a hegemonic power
and india has supplied them with uh
with uh
naval assets like ships and helicopters
etc and we have a very close i'm talking
about mauritius here we have a very
close
strategic relationship with mauritius so
it's a relationship based on mutual
respect and mutual benefit the same goes
with tajikistan tajikistan is a country
in central asia
it is not a turkic country it's in it's
an ironic country they speak i think
persian or dhari or some variant or
dialect of persian
which tells you that india and
tajikistan have very ancient and very
close relations just the way we have
with iran so once again there is a
relationship based on mutual trust
mutual respect and mutual benefit the
same goes for oman
so india first of all would be paying
these nations for the privilege of
hosting an indian base on their
territory and secondly there will be
other considerations as well
based on mutual benefit
that's how
a healthy relationship goes now let's
look at the united states and japan
the united states has
multiple numerous
military bases
in japan most of which have been there
since 1945
and the united states did not negotiate
with japan
for keeping these bases on japanese soil
the americans have not
taken japanese permission for that
the americans defeated japan in world
war ii
they nuked nagasaki and hiroshima
right
they defeated the japanese
they uh allowed the japanese emperor to
stay on as the titular head of state
for their own
for whatever considerations they had
and they forced japan
to adopt a constitution that was written
by the americans themselves or and they
say it was written under us supervision
that's what they say
so it's not
a native indigenous japanese
constitution it's a it's a constitution
that was written under american
supervision
it has certain clauses and things that
prohibit japan from doing certain things
right
and they have had these multiple
numerous military bases air force bases
naval bases marine bases other bases
on japanese territory in multiple parts
of japan across the length and breadth
of japan they've had these bases
since 1945
and they haven't taken japan's
permission for this
understand this please please understand
this is this is these are facts you can
verify them for yourself
for yourselves
similarly let's talk about italy
the italians
were on the losing side in world war ii
they were part of the axis x powers
the axis powers were japan germany
and italy
right so the italians lost
second were the
the war right they lost second world war
and the americans have had bases
military bases
in italy since at least the 1950s so
this is again
a permanent situation so this is what we
mean by military occupation military
occupations means
occupation means you don't take
permission
you tell them this is what's going to
happen this is how it's going to be
deal with it
and then you have a permanent base there
and you don't pay them for the privilege
of doing this
you don't take their permission they
just have to accept things the way they
are so that is the difference between
what india the relationship that india
has with tajikistan
and mauritius and oman and the
seychelles
etc
the relationships india has with these
nations are relationships based on
mutual trust mutual respect mutual
benefit
the relationship that the us has with
japan for instance is a highly
asymmetric relationship
it's a relationship that is based on
coercion and based on is a stark
imbalance of power
so that is what we mean by occupation i
hope i have made this
hopefully clear yes
all right
next
praveen says uh after the after the
russian ukraine war will japan develop
its own nuclear weapons or would it
continue to be under america also why
would a developed country like japan
still remain obedient to america is it
fear of chinese invasion or fear of fat
man and little boy again
japan like i said
is under us occupation it is it doesn't
have a choice
of deciding its destiny it's not like
okay tomorrow i have decided that i will
no longer obey americans it doesn't work
like that
there's a permanent american military
presence in japan
the major power in japan is not japan
it's the us
so it's not like japan has a choice
it's not like japan can decide next week
that we cannot we don't want the
american bases anymore please leave
doesn't work like that
they don't have a choice
all right
and uh you will see these articles in
various uh
media organizations speaking about japan
as a shadow nuclear power so japan has
an excellent
technological base they are one of the
most they are probably the most
technologically advanced nation on the
in the world
and they could
develop new developments next weekend if
they wanted to they have the technology
they can do it
but they will not be allowed to do it
because well that would give them
the
the kind of leverage they have not had
for 70 years
so japan will not be allowed to develop
its own nuclear weapons and who will not
allow them the americans will allow them
why would the americans
allow the creation of a new nuclear
weapon state
they don't want that
right so uh
it's a developed country but it's not a
strong country it's a broken country
it's a country that is
under foreign occupation
and that's why it stays obedient to
america because it has no other choice
it's not that it's it fears the chinese
invasion it's not like if it fear fears
anything like that
of course there is the threat of chinese
invasion and the americans
guarantee the security of japan i mean
as long as they do but it's that they
have no other choice so that's why
they are forced to remain obedient to
the us they are forced to remain under
american hegemony and occupation
and
so yeah that's what it is they will not
be allowed to develop their own nuclear
weapons unless the americans
certainly feel the need for having a
nuclear japan in that case i don't
foresee that happening
okay chetan says
apparently the current government is
preparing well for a true two front war
but is it prepared enough for another
half
front war with the internal enemies i'm
asking this question because
when anti-national protests go on our
government does nothing to end the
protests
if it is not doing enough then what
steps should the government do take to
control them okay so i understand what
you're talking about you're talking
about the uh
what was it called shaheen bag that that
that episode which went on for a few
months and also the the so-called pharma
protests right
and these uh
all these uh episodes
protests whatever you call them happened
in the national capital new delhi they
went on for several months and the
government did not break up the protest
it allowed these protests to continue
why is it so is the indian government
useless
is it powerless or is there something
else to the story that we don't see
you may remember a couple of years ago i
don't remember how long it ago it was
maybe two years ago or so
there was this sudden
apparently spontaneous outpouring of
protests in thailand
students
you know educated students well
educators from college and university
students
affluent students wearing
you know expensive clothing
coming out with play cards and all that
and they
took bangkok essentially hostage
it it happened out of nowhere
these so-called supposedly spontaneous
protests it went on for a while and then
all overnight the protests evaporated
how did that happen it went on for quite
some time just like what happened in
scheinberg and the former protests and
riots and all that
do you know how much
logistics it takes how much planning it
takes how much money it takes
to organize and sustain protests
you need to keep people motivated you
need to ensure that people are there in
place you need to ensure that food is
delivered to them all the facilities are
delivered to them you need to ensure
these people
get paid i suppose
and so on and so forth
it takes a lot of logistics and planning
and resources lots of money to do that
where does all this come from
i wonder
right
so
when these protests happened in india
the shaheen bag thing or the farmer
thing or whatever
the question is
who was behind it who was funding it who
was organizing it who was planning it
who switches it on and who switches it
off
and why did the government not interfere
not intervene in this
because see the thing is this
there are certain powerful forces in the
world that can create protests and
what's called color revolutions
at a moment's notice
they have things in place
in various countries you know assets in
place people in place logistics in place
they have sources of funding where ngos
and all that
and they can
create an eruption of protesting and
violence and all that see what happened
in ukraine in 2014
two new tv stations come up overnight
and start broadcasting certain kinds of
messaging messaging
and thousands of people
are there in the euro maidan square
who's organizing it all who's funding it
all
and what happened in thailand
was it some kind of message to the thai
government
and what about the other so all the
other various color revolutions that
happened who does this
this is a process that is
iteratively perfected the process of
creating a color revolution
so
when a very powerful foreign power
does such things it is best
to just let it simmer down on its own
right because if the government had
used force to disperse
these protests then just imagine what
the international media was waiting for
they were waiting for creating a
tiananmen square kind of story in india
that's what they were waiting for and
the indian government did not give them
the opportunity it
tolerated this nonsense
it happened with the shaheenbag thing it
happened with the so-called former
protests
so this is foreign interference in india
india is not
so powerful that it can resist certain
countries
so right now what we have to do is keep
our head down
abide our time and work really really
hard for the next two three decades
and build up our economy and our power
that's when we'll be able to stand up to
these very powerful
foreign outside forces because they
don't want india to succeed they don't
want india to rise
so right now the government is doing
what is needed if you look at the
history
of china for the longest time they
swallowed all the insults they swallowed
everything that was thrown at them they
were meek they were submissive
and they just kept on working so that's
what india needs to do yes we have
enemies we have enemies outside we have
enemies inside and the enemies inside
are actually an extension of the enemies
outside
so these external enemies are are are
cultivating assets within our country
and they are funding them via via ngos
and what not this is how it works this
is what they do worldwide
and as long as you are a small power as
long as you are not a major global power
you're gonna have to
find
other ways of dealing with this
you know
so that's what india is doing right now
i would disagree that indian the indian
government the current government is not
doing enough
to safeguard india's national security
what it has it is it has done what it is
doing
is the best course of action the prime
minister even took back the the farm
laws because of what was going on
in you have to look at the long-term
perspective
the long-term national interest yes you
may have to
do some
chess sacrifices in the short term so
that you win the chess game in the long
term that's how it goes so i think india
is doing well in that regard
okay um
love your videos and view from the
indian perspective thank you as an
australian can you say how concerned i
should be about china's imperialist
ambitions intentions down under in the
coming 20 years
obviously for many decades we've proven
we have provided a lot of tokenistic
support to the american war machine in
exchange for their protection but i feel
fear it won't be enough
so australia is in the kind of location
where it is kind of exposed let's take a
look at the the map
so here we are we have australia all
alone here in the pacific
ocean
it's very very far away from the united
states the us guarantees australia's
security more or less it's been
australia's security guarantor since the
end of the second world war during the
second world war there was a very very
real
fear in australia of an invasion that
would come in from japan the japanese
navy was very powerful they could have
done that
so
that was the fear at that time today you
have an even more powerful force out
there which is china
the question is would china want to take
over i mean to to invade australia i
don't think the chinese want to go
rampaging
across the world invading countries in
in enslaving them occupying them there
are far better ways of doing it i mean
why why why why can't you just buy out
all the politicians
and then
control the country from outside
right i mean we know what the chinese
have been doing these this debt trap
diplomacy
cultivate various crooked corrupt
politicians in various nations
and buy them out and then have these
ridiculous
loan terms imposed upon the country and
so on so the chinese as we know have
been interfering in australia's internal
affairs they
have been interfering
they have apparently apparently i'm
saying apparently bought out some
politicians and bought out some
lawmakers bought out
some
uh business people and so on so their
tentacles are deep into australia
already
so the chinese the way i see it china
doesn't seek to invade australia and
occupy it
physically there are other ways of doing
it you can do it from far away from by
remote control
so the chinese obviously have this
ambition of replacing and displacing the
us as the sole superpower globally
by 2049 which would be the 100th year of
the chinese communist party is coming
into power
so australia would be part of those
plans of course
so from from australia's perspective
it's it's uh
it's tough days i mean it's gonna be a
tough couple of decades
and coming up for it's gonna be that way
for everyone
with the rise of china you will see the
rise of china's imperial ambitions china
sees itself as the middle kingdom as the
center of the universe as the center of
everything and everybody else needs to
be submissive to them
and the cow tau to the emperor
so uh if america doesn't get its act
together then it will not be able
to guarantee australia's security and
all that from
from china and
so that could be a problem
so that is how the world is going we are
witnessing the very rapid bipolarization
of the world into two camps the american
and nato camp which australia and new
zealand are a part of and
and the other camp which is china russia
and whoever else would want to stick
together with them and the problem is
that for the longest time the the
the
so it's been about 10 to 12 percent of
humanity that has ruled over everybody
else dictated people dictated everybody
else about how to behave how to think
what to say what not to do and so on so
people are kind of fed up of the system
so that
and if you look at the level of sancti
money that you are witnessing right now
post the ukraine invasion it's it's it's
uh turning off even the
most ardent
anglophiles and west files or whatever
right
so they are precipitating this
bipolarization and they are pushing
people into the embrace of china so
that's what we are witnessing now so
the
coming couple of decades are going to be
quite interesting and it's it may be
tough for australia
one hopes that australia remains a
sovereign nation and all hopefully let's
see let's see how it goes but it may not
be that way
okay we fed says right now indo-pacific
is the focus of geopolitics there are
powers like china us russia india uk
france and so on but there's no mention
of new zealand instead of it
being part of indo-pacific is there any
reason behind it
maybe because it's so tiny or there's no
role of new zealand well you're right
you've just answered your own question
new zealand is a tiny insignificant
little nation
but it has no real geopolitical role
it's not a major power it doesn't have a
major military it doesn't have a great
navy
that i mean i'm not sure even even if
they have a navy they would have a coast
guard for sure so uh they have a very
small economy
they are
in austria they are permanently in
australia's shadow
the way australia is in the us's shadow
so there is no
real geopolitical role that new zealand
has to play on the global
scene
so that's why there's no major mention
of new zealand it is part of the india
indo-pacific it is part of the five eyes
alliance which is the u.s canada the uk
australia and new zealand the five major
anglo countries english-speaking
countries where you have people of
english origin
so uh so that's what it is so new
zealand is not a major power in any
sense whatsoever not neither
economically nor militarily nor does it
have a
any geopolitical influence so that's
just how it is so it's it's not a major
power and that's why no one really
mentions new zealand
okay sirujian says as a student in cern
geneva i'm worried if there's a chance
of nuclear attack on europe especially
when europeans are going to protect
whites before us with the increased
sanctions
russia might consider using nukes
how likely is a nuclear fallout given
that russia still hasn't conquered
ukraine completely even after a month
i i would say that the uh probability of
a nuclear exchange a nuclear war
should hopefully be very remote
i mean
nobody wants nuclear war and the
contrary to what the perception in and
the image that's been created in the
western media vladimir putin is not a
madman he's a very rational person he
knows exactly what he is seeking he
knows exactly what he
intends to do with ukraine
and he knows that if he starts a nuclear
exchange there's gonna be nukes raining
down on him as well
so
and and everyone knows
that a nuclear war is lose lose for
everybody nobody wins a nuclear war
nobody wins that what are you gonna
inherit after the new after whoever wins
you're gonna inherit a nuclear wasteland
so i do not foresee
well i hope
and i think it's quite
unlikely that a nuclear exchange would
happen
and if there is a maybe one or two
nuclear weapons being
detonated by mistake or whatever it
should not really uh
cause too much of fallout in europe
i mean i was in geneva when chernobyl
happened 1986 so there was this nuclear
fallout that happened in europe there
was this big
cloud of radioactive debris that flew
across europe
and we kids were told not to go out in
the parks and not to play football in
the grass and so on for a couple of
months for two three months
and that's how it was and then things
went then went back to normal so so the
incident in chernobyl was like like like
the explosion of a tactical nuclear
warhead you know not a major nuclear
blast but a reasonably
a reasonably small one
so even if
there were there were to be maybe one or
two
i'm just saying hypothetically if there
was a nuclear blaster too it would as
long as it is small and contain and it's
just one or two it should not create a
big problem for europe but i don't
foresee that happening nobody is crazy
enough to start a nuclear exchange and
nuclear war so i think
and i hope and i pray that there is no
nuclear war ever
and i don't think anybody is crazy
enough to starve not even kim jong-un i
don't think even he is crazy
so
let's let's hope for the best and i
don't think that's going to happen even
though even though the western media
kind of is clamoring for nuclear war
which is strange and it's it's crazy
so the craziness seems to be emanating
from the western media not from the
russians
anyhow
okay padmaja says in your podcast you
are defending russia um okay i agree
with you but i have a question did they
not destroy our educational system in
our country they funded universities and
in the in the planted strong communists
who in return our history okay
okay first of all i am not defending
russia my perspective is not pro-russia
i'm not biased pro-russia whatever
i'm just saying things as they are
i have explained history
i've explained the history of the
conflict where does the conflict rise
who started the conflict who has been
expanding eastwards
and breaching breaking all the promises
it's not russia right so i'm not
defending russia i'm just saying it how
it is
now
the question is
they did not
so so you are saying that they funded
certain people in india's universities
and planted communists and marxists in
our departments and so on
okay
maybe they did so let's compare the sins
of the two sides
i had said
i had said why should i criticize russia
what did they do to me
did they enslave my country
they did not
did they
like the like the westerners did they
did not did they
starve a hundred million indians to
death in
a number in in hundreds of artificially
engineered famines the russians did not
the british did
right did the russians steal almost 50
trillion dollars worth of my ancestral
wealth that my ancestors and our our
ancestors had
had uh acquired over 10 000 years no the
russians did not do any of that the
british did
and so on and so forth they they they
partisan the british partitioned our
country they broke up our country they
created these divisions that still
persist in india the russians didn't
none of that so on the one hand
you have a nation you have the west
let's see let's call it the west
which has indulged in genocide in india
at least a hundred million indians have
died
they enslaved india they colonized india
they stole almost 50 trillion dollars
worth of our wealth
on the other hand you have the russians
who planted a few
communist agents in india what is the
bigger sin
what is the bigger crime what is a crime
against humanity
genocide 100 million indians dead fifty
trillion trillion dollars worth of
treasure looted or a few
communist agents in india what is the
real crime against humanity
i think the answer is very clear now
when it comes to the russians planting
some agents in india's
academic system and all you know that's
what all countries do they try to
further their own interest
read the arthashastra
understand how geopolitics works
understand how statecraft works
you have
to try and maximize your influence
in other countries
now at that time the russians whether it
is the 1670s whatever it was the
russians were legitimately worried that
india may
drift into the american camp into the
western camp and they wanted india to
remain in the russian camp in the in the
ussr camp
and therefore they sought to mold the
minds of indian students
and make them more pro-russian
pro-soviet pro-ussr and that's why they
funded certain academies and all and
this would not have happened if the
indian government had not allowed this
so i don't blame a foreign power to do
which is trying to do certain things
if the indian government had resisted
that
it would not really have happened
so uh you could also argue like like i
said some time ago that we the the
current government allowed the shaheen
bug thing to happen and so on so forth
because the other power that is doing
that is engineering this is way too
powerful us for us and similarly the
ussr was way way more powerful than
india in the 1960s and so on so that's
how it goes but the ussr did not plunder
india it did not commit genocide in
india it did not steal
50 trillion dollars worth of our wealth
it did not do any of those things it did
not it did not partition india and the
russians don't lecture india today about
right and wrong and morality and ethics
and all that remember what you are doing
you think about your place in history
and so on so forth they do none of that
so if you look at if you weigh the two
things on a scale i mean there's no
question about
who has created who has committed crimes
against humanity
and who is who is to be to be blamed
here
so i'm not defending russia or anything
i'm just saying it how it is
it's my perspective i see things from my
perspective from the indian perspective
you may agree disagree that's fine
that's fine but that's just how it is i
mean these are facts
okay siddhant says uh why should india
try to be a superpower um
there are many european countries that
are
wealthy and happy
we are lacking in both and still we
aspire to be a superpower what are the
benefits of being one we see the us
needs to intervene or invade other
countries to project power and has to
fight cold wars with russia and china
isn't it better to just develop our
economy and self defense
see
if you develop if a nation
the size of india
develops itself to its full potential
develops its economy
and self-defense
it automatically becomes a superpower
right india has historically been the
world's
largest economy historically i think
this is not something controversial at
all it's something everyone accepts
india has historically been the major
economic power globally over a third of
the entire world's gdp
and
if you have that sort of
gdp
your
military is going to be proportionate to
that so it's going to be a massive
military that automatically makes you a
superpower so the question that you're
really asking is why
why should india try to to reach its
true potential should we not stay
below that that's what you're asking
think about it clearly
because india historically has been an
economic etc superpower india had very
high living standards
that's what we know based on the
population and the gdp you divide that
you get per capita gdp and so on so why
should india not reclaim its historical
position why should india be content
with mediocrity
why
okay you say that there are many
european countries who are wealthy and
happy you know ignorance is bliss
ignorance is bliss you can be happy and
reasonably wealthy
but what's really happening in europe
do you know what's happening europe
who is the major power in europe is it
poland is it germany is it france is it
the uk is it portugal is it spain
yeah one major power is russia which is
the other major power in europe the
other major power in europe is none of
these western european countries it is
the united united states
since the second world war the united
states has been the major continental
power in western europe all of these
other nations
are in one way or other
colonies
of the united states either via nato or
via the european union
so uh these countries countries like
germany are under permanent u.s
occupation since 1945 they don't have an
independent foreign policy sure they are
reasonably wealthy that people have
reasonably good relieving standards but
where is the self-determination
i spoke about the national interests
today one of the
main components of the national interest
is self-determination
and cultural integrity
does western europe have
self-determination and cultural
integrity it does not
and therefore this
being wealthy and happy
is essentially
being blissfully ignorant it's like
taking drugs and making yourself happy
and trying to ignore the truth of what's
happening to you
right
so i would say that india needs to be
independent india needs to have its own
independent foreign policy which we are
demonstrating right now to a significant
extent
and india needs to rise to its true
potential india needs to reclaim its
rightful place on the global scene it's
historical
place on the global scene
so that's what we should aspire to do
i don't see anything wrong with aspiring
to be a superpower if you
achieve
if india achieves its uh full potential
economically it's going to be a
superpower whether anyone likes it or
not so that's what india needs to go for
just forget about being a
scary country or a hegemonic country
just
attain
your economic
your full economic potential that will
take care of everything
so
so yeah it is good
it is better to develop our economy and
self-defense but that itself will make
us a supervisor so i hope that answers
the question
okay devon says uh why does china have
so many border disputes are they even
worth fighting for like the aksai chain
region is is it a strategic location or
not
as it is located in a highly inhabited
area
so
you so
he is essentially asking whether aksai
chain is worth fighting for
every inch of our territory is worth
fighting for
think about alaska
the russians owned alaska
they they sold it to the u.s for a very
paltry sum of money they thought it's
just uh
not a blade of grass grows that that's
what nehru said about about exciting
when he gave it up to the chinese
nothing it grows there
that's what he said
similarly the russians were under a
different kind of geopolitical pressure
that's why they divested themselves off
alaska they thought it's just a big
patch of wilderness and bears and fish
and and that's it from forests nothing
else grows there so who cares give it to
the u.s today we find that alaska is one
of the most
rich regions in the whole world
full of natural gas and oil and
timber and other
resources it's incredibly
incredibly rich
so it was a strategic blunder maybe it
was not maybe they were not in a
position to hold on to it or whatever
but that's what happens
so aksai chin may be
a high altitude baron
freezing
desert
but it's our land
it's our territory the chinese hold that
illegally they have acquired it through
force
so when the time is right we will
acquire it back
every inch of our land that was
bequested to us by our ancestors is
sacred we have to fight for it if you
start
uh if you if you start if you allow your
standards to slip
it's a slippery slope
you're gonna first give up sachin
tomorrow they say they will say kashmir
give it up to the pakistanis we will
have peace then peace and bhai character
all that nonsense you think the issue
between india and pakistan is kashmir
you think if you give kashmir up they're
going to be happy and we're going to be
brothers forever hell no
so if you
once you start making concessions
there are gonna be greater demands for
concessions
if you
start negotiating
with the bully
if you start giving in to your bullies
if you start negotiating with terrorists
the demands will increase
if you
give in to a blackmailer the blackmail
will never end it's not a one-time
payment it's a recurring payment that's
how it goes so you we have to fight for
every inch of our territory we need to
give
the message
to whoever it it it concerns that we do
not negotiate with about these things
certain things we simply don't negotiate
about certain lines you cannot cross so
right now we are not in a position to
take back sight chin because we are
still not powerful enough the time will
come
work towards it all of you all of us
that's what we would do we have to pull
together as a nation as a civilization
and ensure that we
um
we attain
our rightful place again once again
in in the global scene now why does
china have so many border disputes
because china is an expansionist
hegemonic nation
china seeks uh global superpower status
and uh
so that's why it has so many border
disputes would you shall we take a look
at the border disputes that the chinese
have
so this here is china
uh they have a reasonably stable border
with north korea but they keep on
claiming certain parts of korea as
historically chinese which means that
they will open up those
claims in the future
now they have a settled border
for now
with russia
in the manchuria etc region
but they almost went to war with russia
about this border it was negotiated and
settled about a couple of decades ago so
it is in this region along the usuri
river
that you had these clashes was it here
was it in dangan island i'm not i don't
remember quite where it was most likely
it was here or one of these islands on
this river
so that's where this happened and the in
the 1960s the russians and the chinese
had these intense border clashes several
hundred soldiers died the russians had
decided to nuke china and then the
americans prevented them from doing that
so this
border even though it is currently
settled even the russians know that this
border issue is current is just dormant
it will be reopened by the chinese at
the appropriate time now when it comes
to mongolia the chinese have swallowed
up half of mongolia they call it inner
mongolia
which and this this entire portion south
of present-day mongolia is historically
mongolian territory
so that's what the chinese have followed
up
they have also swallowed up tibet and
east turkestan
the chinese
this is another portion of the chinese
border with the russians
the chinese have various border disputes
with kazakhstan with kyrgyzstan with
tajikistan as you can see the google
maps also shows this border as dashed
and not
not a straight single line
so there again you have a border dispute
the chinese have been encroaching on
afghan territory in the wakhan corridor
over here there again they have a border
dispute
and obviously they they have this
dispute with india they have
acquired indian territory by force and
they've bought a portion of
kashmir from the pakistanis
uh or in this region over here and of
course they also claim
[Music]
and they may have border issues with
myanmar and vietnam as well they went to
war with mitnam in the late 70s early
80s
and so on they claim taiwan they claim
the entire south china sea they have a
border issue with the philippines
this pratley islands dispute
they have a border dispute with vietnam
they have a border dispute with
indonesia and malaysia there is nobody
they don't have a border dispute with
so they are an
expansionist hegemonic country
the chinese are bullies
and the best way to deal with the bully
is not to negotiate with them but to pay
back in their own coin
so right now india and india is very
clear about what sort of nation the
chinese
are
we seek a predictable
relationship with the chinese and we
have we have to achieve that
by being strong peace through strength
so india needs to develop its strength
then we will have peace with the chinese
akash says the current chinese regime
the ccp is not good for india and
possibly for the entire world
contrasting this with the chinese
kingdoms people often say that the ccp
is a curse on china's historical and
cultural image
is this true or were the chinese
kingdoms just aristocratic versions of
the one party system
what i'm trying to ask is the culture
and religion affect the people of a
country very much we indians are what we
are because of our dharma
how was ancient in medieval china can it
be called a great civilization or was it
a collection of power-hungry barbarians
fighting each other without the presence
of higher values
i would certainly consider china to be
one of the great civilizations it's
it is obviously a much younger
civilization than india's
india is the older and greater
civilization right now china is
economically more powerful militarily
more powerful but we have a certain
equilibrium that we have reached for now
so historically
like like you say akash the chinese
communist party is essentially a
continuation of china's imperial system
so china has this curious phenomenon
called
dynastic cycles
so dynasty rises
it
becomes
it comes to power in beijing they have
emperors
you have a number of emperors in the
dynasty
and it reaches the pinnacle of its power
and then for whatever reason it becomes
very oppressive and there's a or or it
loses what's called the mandate of
heaven
which means it loses the war somewhere
or something like that and the people
feel that yeah this dynasty has lost the
mandate of heaven and then the dynasty
is overthrown
that's what happens always even in other
countries other civilizations so the
dynasty is overthrown then there is a
period of anarchy maybe a century or so
and then a new dynastic cycle rises so
that's how it has always been in china
so the ccp the chinese communist party
is an is is we are witnessing a new
diagnostic cycle
this is also a dynasty it's not a
hereditary dynasty
but
the the
the president of china is essentially
the emperor and the ccp is the dynasty
so the next president will not be the
current president's
offspring it will be somebody else but
it will be within from within the ccp's
inner islands of power
so it's a different form of a dynasty
but it's still a dynasty
so typically a dynastic cycle
would last from anything between 100
years to 3 400 years
so the ccp is going to complete 100
years in 2049
so that's how it is so the chinese
kingdoms were aristocratic versions of
the one party system
and the chinese communist party is a
atheistic version or a 21st century
version or 20th century version of the
old dynastic cycles the chinese emperors
have typically been atheists
uh the the
the uh
values they followed were
usually
a certain
amalgam
of confucianism and legalism legalism is
the stick confucianism is the carrot you
can't see it like that so maybe i'll
explain that in more detail some other
time but that's how it is so it's it's
usually been a balance a certain certain
mix a certain amalgam of legalism and
confucianism i think it was huangdi the
yellow emperor who was a proponent of
legalism which was the brute force
approach
and confucianism and taoism to some
extent is a much milder approach
but all of these approaches are
essentially atheistic approaches
china
for a very long time for the longest
time in the past 2000 years has been a
buddhist country but the emperors have
never
followed buddhism
as the state religion or state culture
it's the people who have followed that
and you have had
local rulers and chieftains who have
followed buddhism but the chinese
emperor in the forbidden city has never
been that way
so that is how china was it is certainly
a great civilization i would certainly
give them that that status it's not like
i'm doing them a favor by doing it they
are all right
is was china a collection of power
hungry barbarians fighting each other
without presence of higher values from
time to time yes
you could say so i think there is an
element of barbarism in everybody in
every culture
if if it is tempered by civilizational
and cultural values it is not quite
visible
when that goes away
then the barbarism comes out to the fore
which we see
in all cultures and
in civilization in the world
at times
at times we see that
so uh china
has at times been a collection of power
hungry barbarians fighting each other
when we when we see the history of china
they have fought lots and lots of wars
what we find is that all of these wars
have been with within themselves
i mean
the great strategist sun tzu
was a great warrior great general and so
on who whom did he fight he fought his
fellow chinese that's what it did if he
indeed did exist
so that's how it is their greatest wars
and the greatest military campaigns have
been
among each other and whenever a great
foreign force has invaded china there
the chinese have invariably lost
like uh edward luthbach would say it
takes
it takes four guys on horseback to
conquer china so that's being a little
little flippant but
kind of kind of uh there's there's a
more than a little grain of truth in
there
so that's what i could say about this
the culture and religion do affect the
country very much every country has a
certain character
the russia the russian nation has a
certain overall character india has a
certain overall character so does china
and so so does the english-speaking
world they also have a certain character
so that's how it goes
okay drisha says i recently learned
about the japanese invasion of china and
saw the real footages of nanjing
genocide which were unbelievably
horrifying probably was in the holocaust
excuse me my questions are have those
tragedies influence the chinese and
making them aggressive as aggressive as
they are today
and why have the the japanese still not
apologized for it why is japanese
barbarism not talked about even though
it is an important part of of second
world war history
okay so i came across these images of
the nanjing
atrocity
a long time ago
it kind of when i first saw that it kind
of ruined my day i think i did not eat
food all day that's how bad it was
so the japanese
behaved in an unbelievably
savage
and brutal and barbaric way there's no
two ways about it
they did
they they
they cast aside all notions of being
human you know they were worse than
animals
the japanese who
who rampaged across asia it was not only
in china that they did did such
atrocities
i mean look at what they did in korea
to women especially and what they did to
prisoners of war in other places
there is this unbelievable
true story of the japanese
executing american prisoners of war and
cannibalizing them eating them i'm not
alive but eating them
and so on and there were atrocities
against indian prisoners of war as well
so the japanese behaved in an
unbelievably horrific barbaric brutal
bastille manner in the second world war
no doubt about it um
why is this why is it not talked about
people do not talk about it especially
the chinese the chinese make it a point
of highlighting
and publicizing what the japanese did in
the second during the second world war
the south koreans also do the same
right
so uh i would not well was
what the japanese did was than the
holocaust i don't think so
i don't think so
the holocaust
had a death toll of how many people six
million was it
i think it's six million jews and indian
origin romani people
i may be off by
a few percent here and there but
something like that so i think if you
look at the magnitude of the death toll
i think the holocaust is worse
but if you look at the imagery that
comes out of the
japanese depredations in asia it's kind
of revolting it makes you want to throw
up
so uh
so the question is
so let's address the question of why did
the japanese do such things i mean the
japanese are traditionally a buddhist
nation
very very strongly buddhist and confused
and not confusion sorry uh it's it's a
mixture it's a syncretic mixture of
buddhism and shinto
right
and the buddhism what we call buddhism
is essentially the entirety of indian
culture they worship
ganesh saraswati all hindu gods and
goddesses
with japanese names and they call it
buddhism and the western world calls it
buddhism it's actually just indian
culture like i said many many times
there is no real difference significant
difference between buddhism hinduism
it's all part of the dharmic umbrella
the japanese japan
for at least 1500 years has been a
dharmic nation
so that has a these are the cultural and
civilization values that are part of
japanese culture you cannot say that
it's a foreign religion that has come
into japan it's been part of their
culture for 1500 plus years they have
accepted it willingly nobody is imposed
imposed on there on them so it's part of
japan
that's what it is so how did these
dharmic people
end up committing such horrific
stomach churning atrocities
right it's because of the meiji
restoration the major emperor in the
19th century decided that he was going
to westernize japan
he thought he decided that japan was too
asiatic too primitive
too backward
and he was enamored with the western
ways industrialization
progress
and so on so he decided
to cast aside
buddhism to cast aside dharmic values
and industrialize and western as the
nation
so he started this reform program called
the meiji restoration he did his best to
stamp out buddhism from japan
did not work
but the legacy of that is that today the
japanese see buddhism
as a foreign religion that is part of
japan today so they don't see it as an
indigenous religion or indigenous way of
life they see it as something that has
come from outside but it's still very
much part of
japanese culture whatever of it is still
practiced today lots of japanese are
atheists today it's a consequence of the
70 plus years of foreign occupation of
japan anyhow that's a different story so
the meiji emperor
embarked upon this uh this program of
westernization of throwing out dharmic
values
he created a westernized
industrial force
a westernized army and that was
continued on with it by his grandson and
so on
so by the time of the second world war
the japanese are they they destroyed the
samurai system which was
the samurais were devout buddhists
they had this code of ethics called
bushido
and that was they would they would die
rather than break that code of ethics
and code of behavior bushido so the
modern
post meiji restoration japanese army had
no such qualms
they
and because they abandoned dharmic
values
that's why they acted like the worst of
savage beasts
that's the reason
why all of these horrific atrocities
happened all across asia whether it's in
korea whether it's in china
or wherever wherever else so it is
certainly talked about the chinese
will never give up an opportunity to
speak about what the japanese did and
neither will the koreans now have the
japanese
not apologize they have apologized
multiple times how many times do you
want today's japanese citizens to
apologize for what their ancestors did
right
and i think the japanese have been
punished enough for what they did in the
second world war
i mean they have been
nuked twice
they were nuked twice they are still
suffering from the consequences
of the radiation that was
emitted by those atomic bombs
and they are still under american
occupation
i think they have been punished more
than enough
and they they are laboring under a
foreign constitution
american written constitution so that's
where it is i think it is too i mean
how many times do you want them to
apologize and then there is this this
uh desire to resist this right there are
certain nationalistic politicians who
want to be unapologetic
because they are sick and tired of being
made to apologize and of laboring under
this backbreaking foreign occupation of
japan so there are certain
currents in japanese politics that are
like they they they want to glorify the
japanese imperial era of the second
world war and so on so there are
obviously in a in a nation you will have
all kinds of different schools of
thought and
so on so forth
so that is highlighted from time to time
and that's used to portray japan as a
nation that is still unapologetic about
what it has done which is not quite the
case the japanese
as a whole as a nation
are kind of very pacifistic
so
that's where we are vis-a-vis japan
okay russia case says
how does any nation decide or act
according to
their national interest
who they who are they counseled by is
there any official department of the
national interest
and who are the people analyzing and
anticipating all of that okay so what
you're saying is that every nation does
have a certain national interest
depending on the nation i mean the
pakistani national interest would be
different from the indian national
interest which would be different from
the chinese national interest which
would be different from the national
interest of ghana or botswana or peru
and so on every country depending on its
geography on its history on its culture
ethnicity and so on and so forth would
have a different
set of
national interests core interests
peripheral interests and so on so forth
so who decides what is the national
interest it's typically the the
government that is in power and the
politicians or politicians who are
at the
who have the decision-making authority
at the highest level they are the ones
who would decide what is the national
interest and it's
look at india's own history
did our so-called
leaders
in the 20th century
truly pursue india's national interest
did we
did mr nehru pursue india's national
interests did he promote and further
india's national interest
he embarked upon this
path of fabian socialism
he stifled the indian economy it grew at
one percent or two percent per year the
neheruvian rate of growth
he
imposed this enormous web of
bureaucratic red tape on india is that
following india's national interest no
so very often you will have leaders
who are kind of
well what what polite word do would you
like me to use about the great shari
nehru
well let's say clueless incompetent i
think that's the nicest thing you can
say about him and similarly there are
lots of other countries which whose
leaders don't
pursue
don't promote don't further the national
interest there are these all these
despotic little tin pot dictators in
africa
who are
the fruit
of
the century or so of colonization of
africa africa has been divided up into
artificial nations which don't recognize
ancient tribal
and ethnic divisions so you have civil
wars you have these dictators that are
propped up by european and western
powers
and these dictators
don't care about the national interest
these are artificially created nations
so they don't care about the national
interest they care about enriching
themselves so it's very easy
to influence such people look at the
chinese debt trap diplomacy across the
world
they go into these poor countries which
are run by these dodgy characters
they use checkbook diplomacy
they give them whatever money they want
and then they
have them sign off on these ridiculous
loan terms
so there are lots of countries whose
leaders do not
follow the national interest they do not
act according to the national interest
so they enrich themselves and their own
family
and they
ruin the nation in the pro
in the process
see what happened to sri lanka sri lanka
was entrapped by the chinese it's now
the indians who are having to bail sri
lanka
so there is no official department of
the national interest
in any country that i know of
it's it's it's about the kind of
system that you have
is your system good enough
is your system so good that it throw it
it gives you
leader after leader who knows what the
national interest is and who will act
according to the national national
interest
does your system throw up competent
leaders does your system throw up
excellent leaders or is your system hit
and miss
sometimes you will have a good leader
sometimes you will have a terrible
leader who will undo decades of good
so it depends on that right
so that's how it goes i mean if you look
at thousands of years of history you
will find that you have empires that
rise and fall
empires that rise and fall if you look
at india's history in the past 2000
years you two and a half thousand years
you had the mauryan empire it rose
it made india great then it crumbled
then you had pusher mitra in sunga in
his empire which was rather short-lived
then you had the kushan empire which
reached its zenith during the time of
the great emperor kanishka and then the
kushan empire also crumbled then you had
the gupta empire then you the empire of
the karkotas then you had the chola
empire then you had the
invasions and then you had the murat
empire the maratha empire
could have been so great it freed india
from foreign occupation and then they
fell because of
because of the wrong kind of leaders
that came up weak leaders and so on
so that's how it goes
so it's always a cyclical thing so
eventually in any such cycle you will
have leaders who do not act according to
the national interest or who are not
strong enough that they can do it who do
not know how to
control the levels of power and then
things go
astray
so that's how it is
abhishek says how legit is this
happiness index report that's making the
rounds on social media right now showing
india to be ranked at 136 in the world
what variables does it use to come up to
this to come to this conclusion and is
it a fair assessment of the ground
reality
these reports and indices that the
western world throws up are based on god
knows what i don't know i mean if you
want to measure the happiness
coefficient of happiness index of a
certain nation i would expect that you
would need to do a detailed survey on
the ground have a significant
statistical sample of the population not
just one city but across the length and
the breadth of the country and you would
need certain scientific indices that you
need to
uh evaluate
now is there a universally recognized
index
of happiness i mean what
is it that constitutes happiness
is happiness a scientific thing can you
define happiness scientifically
i think it depends from person to person
what i consider to be happiness you may
you may not consider that to be
happiness so
so there's no scientific definition of
happiness first of all
there is no consensus in the scientific
community about what constitutes
happiness what factors come when they
come together the overall define
happiness and happiness of that right
so these people they come up with these
rankings and all that based on their
whims and fancies
based on god knows what data
what is the sample they've selected to
come up with this thing within india and
and how many people did the survey in
india are they serving the same number
of people in each country
are they doing a proper scientific
survey
what is the methodology is it uh based
on interviews
is is it based on some other indices or
data how is it done i have no idea
i mean tomorrow i could come come up
with
an index that ranks the democracies of
the world according to
my perception
i i'm sure i could come up with a very
scientific definition of what is a
strong democracy and what's a weak
democracy let's call it the cauda index
of democracy should i do that
i'm sure it'll make a lot of people
unhappy
so you know that's how it is done we
don't need to take all of this seriously
the world
is unfortunately very accidentalist very
eurocentric it's all based upon their
perception of what happiness is
i mean these are some of the unhappiest
countries in the world the western
countries
so i i don't take this take this
seriously at all it is not a fair
assessment of the ground reality
and these indices etc are actually used
for geopolitical purposes to paint your
country as either being undemocratic or
fascist or unhappy and so on so forth
and that is used to create certain
perceptions of certain countries
globally
so we should not take these things
seriously
sachin says i have always wanted to know
what which civilization is the oldest
indian or egyptian
the oldest
known civilization in the world
is the indian civilization
the oldest
continuously existing civilization in
the world is the indian civilization
the beginnings of india's civilization
go back at least 10 000 years how do i
make this claim on what basis do i make
this outlandish claim
well let's look at the archaeological
record
in the western region of india indian
subcontinent which includes pakistan
balochistan afghanistan and so on
the so-called
sindhu region which once had seven
rivers great rivers
and that's where we had the so-called
harappan phase of our civilization or
the saraswati hindu phase of our
civilization
they also call it the indus valley
civilization it's not a separate
civilization it's a phase of india
civilization so that is the oldest phase
of india's civilization and
how old is it
so there are thousands of unexplored
archaeological sites that date back to
this era
the oldest
known
such archaeological site is the site of
bhiranna
in
i think it's in haryana today
and it has been carbon dated
to be about
nine and a half thousand years old
so
it was inhabited
9.5 000 years before today
and there are thousands
of unexplored sites all across the
length and the breadth of the saraswati
hindu basin the saptas in the region so
if the oldest site that we know of is
nine and a half thousand years old
and we have explored maybe one percent
of the sites one could
with reasonable confidence claim
that this
phase of our civilization was at least
10 000 years old
most likely it was maybe 20 000 years
old who knows
we will know only when our
archaeologists get to work and do what
they are paid for so
our civilization dates back at least ten
thousand years minimum and what is
remarkable is that there is cultural
continuity that dates back ten thousand
years elements of culture that were
discovered
in beran and other other places
are still visible today
in india in day-to-day life
so you can look look at my other videos
and
you will find the details there so
india's culture
has continuously existed for ten
thousand years indian civilization is at
least
that much old egypt
dates back to maybe four thousand five
thousand bc it's very old no doubt but
not quite as old as india
china dates back to maybe
1500 bc maybe 2000 bc which means it's
about 4 000 years old let's give it 5
000 years so maybe if china is about 5
000 years old egypt may be six maybe
seven thousand years old
at the
at the most
india is way way way older than that
so the oldest civilization is without
any doubt whatsoever
indian civilization
okay pawan says in my history book it is
written that christian missionaries
played a significant role in promoting
language literature and art is it true i
want to know
your history textbook in this state in
this case
is absolutely right
christian missionaries played a very
significant role in promoting language
in promoting literature and promoting
art the only question you have to ask
yourself is which language did they
promote
whose literature did they promote and
what forms of art did they promote
did they promote indian languages
did they promote indian literature
did they promote indian art and culture
or did they promote foreign languages
foreign literature and foreign art
that's the only question you have to ask
yourself
so technically your textbook is right
they promoted language literature and
art the only problem is that they tried
to impose foreign languages foreign
literature foreign religion and foreign
art upon indians and that succeeded to a
significant extent it is
a work in progress
a demographic re-engineering project
that's still in progress right now
so that is the truth they played a very
significant role and they are still
playing a very significant role in
promoting culture
and language literature
foreign culture language literature art
and they're doing it at the expense of
indian languages indian literature
indian art look at the language i'm
speaking in this is called mental
colonization we are all a consequence of
all this
next
ganesh says as per asabiah theory by ibn
khaloon
in dynastic politics of power a
third or maximum fourth generation loses
the power completely but mughal sub
successfully kept power to themselves
for up to six generations barber touring
zip how what did they do differently so
i haven't read the asabiya theory by ibn
khaloon
or the mukaddama that he
published
so i don't know exactly what he said but
let's say he stated that in dynastic
politics three or four generations you
have power and then they lose power
well if you look at indian history that
doesn't hold true at all the mauryan
empire the more in dynasty had
way more than four generations who
stayed in power most likely more than
ten
if you look at the kushan
empire the kushan dynasty you had like
15 or so rulers
who
were in power in the same dynasty the
same goes for the guptas
you had
shri gupta gather
i'm sure i got the sequence not quite
right but you had a large number of
rulers
they were not all
emperors of all india but they were in
power
right so the dynasty lasted a
significant amount of time you had lots
of iterations general generation of the
dynasty which were in political power
and the the same goes for the chula the
chola the chola dynasty was in power for
1500 years
approximately
they were not always emperors
at some times at some points in time
they were
small chieftains at a district level or
so but they stayed in power it in some
way or the other and it's it's one of
the longest ruling dynasties in the
whole world
there weren't emperors of india in
southeast asia for 1500 years that was a
small phase
in the 10th and 11th centuries but this
dynasty would have had hundreds of
generations
right
so
these uh
theories don't always hold true this is
not a scientific theory it's more like a
conjecture that even the khaloon came up
with
and he came up with this conjecture most
likely in the context
of the islamic world
maybe
i'm not sure
where what time period it was and all
but there is a different context
compared to india even if you look at
the japanese their their current dynasty
has
lots of
uh yeah is many many generations old
so that's how it goes right so it's not
like a rule of thumb it's not something
like a
law that's set in stone
it depends from place to place in
certain cultural contexts you will have
lots of generations in a dynasty in
certain cultural contexts you may have
maximum three or four generations it all
depends
that's how it goes
is it true that hindus or brahmanas were
not allowed to cross the sea according
to hinduism which is one of the reasons
that caused the first war of
independence we are referring to 1857.
so
in the rig veda there is a mention of
ships and samudra
in the shattapata brahmana which is a
vedic text there is a reference to ships
that have a hundred ores
we know for a fact
that
indian
genetic lineages
were introduced into australia about
5000 years ago
australia is in the middle of the
pacific ocean
how did indian genetic lineages
make an introgression into the
australian gene pool 5000 years before
today
it means indians went there by
by sea they crossed the sea and went to
australia
it is known for a fact
that indian zebu cattle first appeared
in africa
almost 10 000 years ago and there was a
second wave of indian zebu cattle
coming into africa egypt to be more
specific about four thousand years
before today
and we know that the whole of eastern
africa
has a very strong indian culture and
influence the only way to to reach
indian east africa from india
is by sea
right
i mean
if you talk about somalia kenya tanzania
mozambique madagascar
and so on you have a very strong indian
cultural and genetic influence there the
genetic influence is not yet proven
because nobody has done genetic analysis
of these people but it will come in time
so indians
have been going
and trading and communicating and maybe
living in eastern africa for for
most likely thousands of years
it is known that indian merchants traded
with egypt
two thousand years before today and
maybe most likely much before that as
well
it is also known that indian traders
wealthy indian traders
would trade with rome in roman ports
they would go there by sea from indian
ports
they would
give the romans they would sell to the
romans whatever the romans wanted from
india and they would take back gold from
rome rome in return
so india
has always been
a maritime nation a great maritime
nation a seafaring nation
india has always been that
the cholas
the
brahmanas the kalingas
the kalinga kingdom
also had brahmins
the kalingans had been trading with
southeast asia
for at least 3000 years before today
they are the ones who first introduced
indian culture in hinduism into
southeast asia and the cholas followed
suit about a thousand years before today
and the cholas had a magnificent
maritime
empire
they had the most powerful navy on the
surface of the planet at that time
the cholas were hindus they were not
some secular
empire
right
so that's how it is so
it is absolutely incorrect
i mean i know this claim is made in
indian history textbooks and all that
these are lies these are incredible lies
india has always been a maritime and
seafaring nation what
possibly happened is this
the past 1000 years
are what i call india's millennium of
humiliation india came under foreign
occupation first turkic occupation
and then european occupation and the
turks caused this
incredible cultural and demographic
genocide in india
hundreds of millions of indians died
it's not documented
i'm sure we can figure out the actual
numbers
but india's historians are
they will not talk about this right so
you had this horrific genocide that
happened over about a period of about
five centuries
so the minimum death toll would have
been 100 million maximum could be way
above 500 million and
it's happened over five centuries 500
years so that these numbers do make
sense okay
and then you had the genocide that
happened at the hands of the british at
least 100 million indians died there
so over a period of a thousand years you
have maybe 500 or million or more
indians dying in these horrific
repeated genocides
so in such
an environment
it became incumbent on all men
to stay at home you cannot go
to foreign countries on ships you have
to stay at home and you to protect your
family you to protect the honor and the
security of your family and your of your
relatives and so on
so maybe that is why it became
considered to be bad for indians or
hindus
to cross the sea and go abroad stay at
home
defend your family so maybe something
it's something that emerged over the
past thousand years that it is a bad
thing to go and cross the sea and go
abroad stay at home and defend your
defend your family and defend the honor
so maybe it's something more recent
because historically there is absolutely
no doubt about this that india has
always always been a major
maritime seafaring nation and culture
and civilization
whoa that's a big
big
question
anurag says
i have more than one question i think
there are three here i've taken two
so uh i came across two statements first
some chinese sources have mentioned that
the great was there vasa the tongue
empires for assal
second is that some sources have
mentioned that the rajput ruler
was a vasal of lalith
and fought against the arabs on his
behalf i don't know how authentic these
statements are could you throw some
light on this remarks
so it is known that the tongue
empire claimed that
was their vasal that's what they claimed
well the chinese claimed that everybody
was their vasal and that they were the
center of the universe that's what they
claimed
it doesn't mean it's it's facts the
chinese the tang dynasty the tang empire
also called india tanju
which means the center of heaven
and at that time the greatest emperor in
india
was
the peda he conquered most likely much
of central asia
and sindh and much of india as well
so he had an enormous empire that would
rival that of kanishka the great
so such
an emperor would not be the wasall of
the tongue
there certainly would have been
diplomatic relations and so on
and maybe the tongue would like to
embellish facts in their own historical
records it doesn't mean that these
claims have
any significant basis in reality so the
fact is that
was not anybody's vasal he was a great
emperor in his own right
and he had diplomatic relations with the
tongue
so that's how it is about
i am not quite sure i haven't really
studied this history of baba rawal and
his relationship with other kings and
rulers
there is in in fact a very significant
paucity
of information of literature about baba
raval so i am not quite sure about that
i know
i don't have
sufficient
knowledge as of today about this so
maybe i can revisit this in the future
okay the next question is during the
period between the third and the sixth
century
there were three adjacent neighboring
great powers the romans the sasanians
and the guptas correct
while the romans and the sasanians were
engaged in continuous large-scale
conflicts
uh contrary to it there were no such
problems between between the guptas and
the sassanians why is that
please give me an answer
this is an interesting question
so
so let's understand who the sassanians
were the sassanians were our persian
cousins
so the sasanian emperor empire was
located in iran
and they had this
long standing conflict going on with
the western nations whether it is greek
or whether it is greece or later on the
romans because the romans eventually uh
conquered greece and therefore they came
into conflict with the persians
so during this period that you speak
about there was indeed this uh conflict
between uh the sasanians and the romans
it was an ongoing conflict it just went
on and on
and it's curious it's quite curious that
there was no significant conflict at any
period in time
between india and persia whether it is
be during the manish empire the cabinet
empire
or the susannian period or whatever
right it's only after the islamization
of iran that the
that the relations deteriorated between
india and iran and you had conflicts
later on
so i am not quite sure why it is the
case maybe it is this
cultural and ethnic affinity that india
and portugal had in the old days that
prevented any such escalation or any any
such
incident or conflict
because it's true
the persians always concentrated on
expanding westwards and entering into
conflict with western
cultures the greeks and the romans
they never ever had any significant
conflict with indians
ever it is known that the royal house
the the rios
uh claimed that he had
some part of it of western india as part
of his empire
so
that would probably be parts of
balochistan or some parts of afghanistan
because afghanistan gandhar has
historically always been part of india
and so on but there was never any
conflict
between india
and iran on any substantial scale so i
don't know why i don't think any
historian has even tried to answer that
the same way no historian tried to
answer why chinggis khan never tried to
invert india they decided not to in
media so maybe that's something i should
give some thought to and figure out why
before the islamization of persia
the persians never tried to invade india
or enter into any kind of conflict with
india because india was not always
unified under a great empire
we had these imperial phases the
mauryans the koshans even the sketians
at some point in time indus keithians
and then you had the makshatrapa and all
then the guptas and so on so forth but
there were times when india was not
unified under a single empire and even
in those during those periods the
persians did not attempt ever
to invade india or enter into a conflict
so that's a curious
fact historical fact so anurag thank you
for asking this question it is something
i need to think
more
about and maybe i will make a video
about that in the future but it's a very
interesting question that you asked
okay ruthless says wow it's a long long
long question
okay i had a history question william
jones
henry thomas colebrook and so on so
forth all had this conviction to
encourage sanskrit and arabic knowledge
in india they had a belief that if we
want to rule india in a better way we
have to go with their perception
such people who wanted to encourage
sanskrit and arabic culture were termed
orientalists
people like thomas babington mcauley
james mill obstructed such practices and
insisted that the british government
stopped investing
money in such projects and notions
what if the orientalists led india with
their ideology
what was the scenario of india if there
were no european customs what would be
the plot of the education system in
today's world
okay thank you good question
so uh i don't know about arabic arabic
is not an indian language it doesn't
have any
any any
locus standard in india it's a foreign
language it belongs in arabia where it
should prosper but it has no
no reason to be in india now when it
comes to sanskrit sanskrit is the medium
in which india's education has
historically always been until the 19th
century when the macaulays and the the
english destroyed india's education
system and replaced it with this
colonial system
so if the orientalists had prevailed
then india's indigenous education system
would most likely have persisted and we
would all be way more civilized today
not westernize the the way we are so
that's the answer in short india would
have been a much better place i would be
speaking to you in sanskrit right now if
that's what would have happened
but as we know macaulay and his minions
prevailed and they essentially destroyed
india's education system and
deracinated india and that process still
continues as of today
akash says this one is personal i'm sure
it's important for everyone to know how
do you keep your mind stable peaceful
and productive in the modern world of
toxicity left right debate
geopolitical issues etc how do you not
let your interests clash with your goals
in your personal life
how do i keep my mind mind stable
peaceful productive well
once mind is not always stable peaceful
productive you obviously have emotions
uh things affect you of course i have
always been a very positive person i
have never had any
so these days it's very fashionable to
talk about mental illness and
depression and all these things
well i personally have never ever
experienced any of these things
i've never
personally met somebody with a mental
illness or depression i've never
experienced these things i am a very
positive person a very cheerful person
look everybody goes through ups and
downs i have also gone through ups and
downs it's not like
everybody has this stable constant
plateau or constant progress
one goes through ups and downs in life
and one has to deal with that
so uh
maybe it's part of who i am my
my personality my nature but i'm a very
positive person even when things are not
well i am
positive i'm optimistic and i work
towards
progress so
that's
just the way i am i don't have any great
secret of how i do this
uh
how do i not let my interests clash with
my goals and personal life you know what
there is no such separation or
compartmentalization of your
professional life in your personal life
your life is your life it all
comes together in one person
so people talk about work life balance
and keeping work at in the office and
going home and having family life at
home and so on that that's not quite how
it works
it all
you cannot compartmentalize your life
so in my case it's all together i've
never tried to keep things separate that
when i'm at home i should not think
about certain things or not talk about
certain things
not do certain things and so on
so
i just go with the flow
i'm an easy going guy
i'm a happy guy
so that's just just how it has been with
me
i have a reasonably stable mind
peaceful mind
and yeah the world is full of toxicity
there is this political debate left
versus right geopolitical issues but i
have known
well for essentially forever since i've
been around
that's the nature of the world
there is good as well as bad in the
world increasingly there is more bad but
that's how the world always has been i
am a student of history as much as i'm a
student of science i am i know what
history has been like the history of the
human species is a history of warfare
and conflict so it doesn't surprise me
that you see what we see
in the world today so i am at peace with
that
i try to do what i can and
let's see how it goes
so
that in short is the answer
right okay let's take a couple of
questions more
ishaan says how can i become a good
auditor like our current prime minister
mr modi
okay so
how do you become a good
athlete you practice
how do you become a good boxer
you practice how do you become a good
swimmer
you practice
how do you become a better chess player
you practice how do you become a better
orator you practice you practice
practice practice practice
so if you want to become a better
speaker a better auditor
spend some time every day speaking
about some topic go and stand in front
of the mirror and speak
and see how it feels
or maybe you could take a camera and
record yourself speaking and do that
every single day maybe 10 minutes a day
or whatever
our current prime minister mr modi has
been doing this for 50 years i i'm sure
the best the best part of five decades
public speaking day in and day out it's
practice that makes you better you
slowly improve over time some people are
born with talent some people do not have
certain kinds of talent talent is
overrated it's the hard work the
discipline that you put in that really
makes you who you are
you put in the hours you put in hour
after hour you put in hundreds of hours
you're going to improve
so that's what you have to do
all right um
one more question two more questions
um
anime says is it really fair to expect
everyone to become an entrepreneur or
have that mindset is it really bad to
lead a simple life
some people perform exceptionally well
when they are given a protected work
environment
in that case are they not contributing
towards building a community of course a
country in any way at all i feel not
everyone is cut out to handle the
immense pressure or
born with the risk taking appetite
the entrepreneurs have to go through
your thoughts i i think you're
absolutely right most people do not
have what it takes to be an entrepreneur
and there's nothing wrong with that
entrepreneurs probably make up
maybe
two to five percent of society
the people with the appetite for risk
the appetite for whatever it takes to be
an entrepreneur and most of the people
are happy to have a protected stable
work environment and there is absolutely
nothing wrong with that
not everybody should try to be an
entrepreneur
don't chase the latest fad in fashion
shark tank so everybody should be an
entrepreneur no no no no without the
people
who need the protected work environment
without the people who seek to work the
nine-to-five job and so on
without those people there cannot be
entrepreneurship because entrepreneurs
need employees reliable good employees
will do the work
so there's a place for everything
in any high performing productive
society there's a place for
entrepreneurs there's a place for people
who would rather like to
lead a stable protected life and be
productive in their own way there's a
place for everybody in a good society
and most people
are not meant to be entrepreneurs and
that's perfectly fine
so
that's just how it is so you don't need
to have the mindset and it's not bad to
live a simple life it's actually very
nice
to live a simple steady peaceful
productive life
so everybody needs to figure out what's
best for them what is their aptitude
like
and then pursue that
okay this is the last one for today they
just said they just says how can one
bring discipline to do things
consistently every day in life you build
discipline by starting very small
let's say you want to become a
bodybuilder just a hypothetical example
you you need to start by doing two
push-ups every day
make sure you do it every single day for
let's say 10 days just do two push-ups
and then you're done so you're building
a habit
then for the next 10 days do five
push-ups per day and build upon that
build upon these slow small habits the
japanese have this thing called kaizen
right the power of compounding you start
with very small habits but build habits
consistent habits don't break the habit
let's say you want to broaden your
intellectual horizons
then
make sure that you read you start small
i'm gonna read two pages every day
that's it just two pages do it for a
month
then double it instead of two i'm gonna
read five
slightly more than double so do that for
a month and slowly slowly build up the
habit the stamina the intellectual
mental stamina for reading so you that's
how you build discipline if you start
with enormous goals you're gonna give up
immediately
you're gonna get disheartened so start
with very small things start with
something that doesn't take much
resistance from inside
and then you make then you then you
build up on that so that's how you build
discipline to do things consistently
start small always start small make it
easy for yourself to build a habit so
don't start with something difficult
start with something very very easy and
it becomes second nature if you start
doing it every day and then make it
progressively
more impactful
uh anime says you always encourage us to
become the best version of ourselves how
do i know if i've become the best
version of myself are there any telltale
signs
comparison could be a vicious cycle in
itself if i compare myself with you my
heart sings and so on
don't get me wrong and yeah
i'm never gonna be as great as you are
this shouldn't stop me or anyone from
striving to become better should it
how can one get over that feeling of
comparison you know what
it's perfectly fine to compare yourself
you are
part of society you gotta see other
people
you obviously will compare yourself with
them
and try to measure up where they stand
where i stand and where you stand
absolutely nothing wrong with that
secondly how to become the best version
of yourself listen it's a it's a work in
progress you don't become the best
version of yourself in a week or a month
it's a lifelong process
so identify
something that you would like to improve
it and then like i said build small
habits build the discipline
and over time over
five years or ten years over decade or
two decades you will improve you'll get
better
and
after a while you'll you will feel you
will find that you want to improve
something else
now you've overgrown you've outgrown
that that initial
uh desire to become better at this then
you will try to find something else to
be better at as you grow
and that's how it goes so it's it's a
never-ending process it's not like
you realize one day that i have become
today the best version of myself no it's
not like that am i the best version of
myself i'm not
i have a long way to go so it's that's
how it is
the moment you stop growing
stop stop feeling that you have to
improve that's the moment you you become
an old person
right so always
try to
improve yourself it's perfectly fine to
compare yourself with other people
there's nothing wrong with that
and that should not dishearten you
so
find two or three people whom you really
admire ask yourself what are the traits
that you admire in those people and then
ask yourself how can you
emulate some of those aspects and then
build small habits and make them grow
over time so maybe that's one of the
ways to become the best version
of yourself
all right my friends that is it for
today thank you very much for all the
questions thank you very much for your
viewership i really appreciate it
and we're gonna keep continuing this
but that is
it for tonight
so
take care good night i will see you next
time